Guide to the Evelyn Davis Papers and Photographs WAG.245
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Evelyn Davis Papers and Photographs
1885-1982
1940-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Davis, Evelyn
WAG.245
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton.
Evelyn Davis (1906-1982) was an actress in theater, TV, and film beginning in 1933 and continuing throughout her life. She appeared in supporting roles in numerous Broadway and touring productions. Later in her career, she worked more steadily in television and film. Davis was a member of various theater associations, including Actors' Equity Association, Screen Actors Guild, and the Negro Actors Guild of America, for which she served as a member of the Executive Board and as Recording Secretary. The collection contains scripts, playbills, news clippings, and contracts from her various performances, as well as documents reflecting her organization memberships. Also included are personal correspondence and memorabilia, material on theater history, photographs, and a scrapbook.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Evelyn Davis (1906-1982) was born and educated in New York City where she lived throughout her life. Before embarking on an acting career, Davis was a teacher, and later she worked as a model. In 1933 Davis joined the Hall Johnson Choir and appeared in Run Little Chillun!, a lyric drama by Hall Johnson. Her resume includes several Broadway plays: Happy Birthday and The Wisteria Trees with Helen Hayes, "Vicki" with Jose Ferrer, and "The Perfect Marriage" with Miriam Hopkins. Touring productions include Macbeth with Orson Welles and The Naked Genius with Gypsy Lee Rose. Davis continued to be cast in plays throughout the 1950s before venturing into minor roles in television and film. On television Davis appeared in the Omnibus production of Uncle Tom's Cabin and the NBC production of The Iron Gate. Her film credits include small roles in Shaft, "Nothing but a Man, Shaft's Big Score, and Final Cut.
Davis was also active in various theatrical organizations: Actors Equity Association (AEA), the American Federation of Television and Radio Actors (AFTRA), the Screen Actors Guild (SAG), and the Negro Actors Guild of America (NAG). Before her health began to fail, Davis was on the NAG-New York Branch Executive Board and also served as its Recording Secretary. In 1969, Davis was a delegate to SAG's Joint Equality Committee, which held a series of discussions on the issue of casting ethnic minorities in television commercials. Davis died on January 30, 1982 at Harlem Hospital in New York City.
Related Archival Materials
For more information about the Negro Actors Guild of America, see the Negro Actors Guild of America Records in the New York Public Library.
Scope and Content Note
The Evelyn Davis Papers and Photographs consists of Evelyn Davis's personal papers and memorabilia. Her extant papers reflect a life-long interest in the history of African-Americans in theater and film. The bulk of the collection is made up of scripts, playbills, and contract agreements from Davis's appearances in plays and television programs throughout the 1940s, '50s, and '60s. There are also papers from organizations to which Davis belonged, including a membership card from the Screen Actors Guild, a membership certificate from the Negro Actors Guild of America, and contracts from the Actors' Equity Association. The collection also contains letters, cards,and telegrams from family and friends, including actors with whom Davis worked. Illuminating Davis's interests are several collections of Negro spirituals, an essay on racial prejudice by Dr. Juan Rene Betancourt, an issue of Theater Arts entitled "The Negro in the American Theater," and a booklet, "The Way It Was," that commemorates African-American actors and actresses. The collection also includes two photograph albums that have been disassembled and one intact photograph album (largely black and white prints for all three), one disassembled scrapbook, and ninety loose black and white photographs ranging in size from 11x14 to 2x3 inches. Included in the photographs are signed headshots from other actors and actresses and stills of theater performances.
Arrangement
Folders arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in repository; provenance is unknown. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1950.128, 1985.024 and NPA.2005.227.
African Americans in the performing arts.; Theater history |y 20th century.; Actresses -- United States.; African Americans in television.; Playbills.; Correspondence.; Screenplays; Telegrams; Scrapbooks.; Contracts; Photographs.; Actors -- Labor unions -- United States.; Negro Actors Guild of America; Actors' Equity Association; Davis, Evelyn; Screen Actors Guild
- Actors Equity Association: Contracts, 1939-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Anta Album: Program, May 6, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Betancourt, Dr. Juan Rene, "Integral Sociology: The Scientific Improvement of the Racial Prejudice", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Black Academy of Arts and Letters, Oct 8, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Burleigh, H.T. (arranger): Negro Spirituals, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Clippings, undated, 1949, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Communication in Black Culture": Sponsored by Bell System, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Contracts: General, 1939-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Copasetics: "The Way It Was" (souvenir journal), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1943-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Daily Voucher, Nov 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- DiTullio, Eileen, in concert: Advertisement, Nov 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Duet": Program, Aug 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Essays, 1935, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Flamingo Road": Program, Mar 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Frey, Hugo (arranger): Celebrated American Negro Spirituals, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Godmother for Amy": segments of script, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Happy Birthday" with Helen Hayes: Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Happy Birthday" with Joan Blondell: Program, Jun 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Hat, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Headshots, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "Iron Gate": Program, Aug 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Jubilee Singers (Fisk University): Program, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "King of Hearts": Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Landlord": Call Sheet, Jul 28, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - NYC Board of Education certification, 1919 (Box Shared Tamiment 044, Folder 5)
- Loose Photographs (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Male Animal": Program, Aug 1948, Aug 1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Memorabilia, undated; 1919 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Metropolitan Council on Housing, Feb 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "Naked Genius": Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- National Council of Senior Citizens, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Negro Actors Guild of America, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Negro Actors Guild of America: "A Tribute to Marian Anderson", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Negro Actors Guild of America: Certificate of Membership, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- New York City Civil Service: Retired Employees Association, undated (Box 11, Folder 35)
- Nigerian Pogrom: Crisis 1966: Vol. 3 (Ministry of Information, Eastern Nigeria) (Box 1, Folder 36)
- "No Time for Comedy": Program, Jul 1952 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Notice of Result: On-the-Job Survey (NYC, Dept. of Personnel: Hospitals Dept.), Jul 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Obituary, Sep 1982 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Ojukwu, Lieutenant-Colonel Odumegwu: "On Aburi We Stand: A Broadcast", Feb 25, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- "Old Acquaintance": Program, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Oversize Headshots (Box Tamiment Shared OS002)
- Performance Stills (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Photograph Album #1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Photograph Album #2: Contents and Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 44)
- "Ponder Heart": Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- "Railroads on Parade": Book of the Pageant, New York World's Fair 1939 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Receipt: Office of the Comptroller, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Reel 1: Publication of Screen Actors Guild-New York Branch (E.D. p. 6, p. 14), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Resume, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- "Rossiter M.D.": Script, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- "Run Little Chillun!": Program, Nov 1933 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Scrapbook: Contents (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Scrapbook: Cover (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Scrapbook: Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Screen Actors Guild: Conservatory Program, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Screen Actors Guild: Membership Card, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Screen Actors Guild: Producers Pension Plan, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Script: Hertz Commercial, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Snapshot Album (Box 1, Folder 59)
- "Sound of Silence": Program and Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
- "Southern Exposure": Program and Script, Oct 1950 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Statement of Annuity Savings Account, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Telegrams, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Television Program: Audition, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Television Program: Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Theater Arts: The Negro in American Theater, Vol. 26, No. 8, Aug 1942 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- United States Civil Service Commission: Notice of Rating, Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- "Vicki": Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Williams, John D.: "Hallelujah" and "Why Should I Fear", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- "Wisteria Trees": Program, Jul 1954, Feb 1955 (Box 1, Folder 70)